    <para>
      Plotting support is only available in the graphical GNOME version.
      All plotting accessible from the graphical interface is available from
      the Create Plot window.  You can access this window by either clicking
      on the Plot button on the toolbar or selecting Plot from the Calculator
      menu.  You can also access the plotting functionality by using the
      <link linkend="genius-gel-function-list-plotting">plotting
      functions</link> of the GEL language.  See the chapter on
      <link linkend="genius-gel">GEL Basics</link> to find out how to
      enter expressions that &appname; understands.
    </para>

    <sect1 id="genius-line-plots">
      <title>Line Plots</title>
      <para>
	To graph real valued functions of one variable open the Create Plot
	window.  You can also use the
        <link linkend="gel-function-LinePlot">LinePlot</link> function
	on the command line (see its documentation).
      </para>
      <para>
	Once you click the Plot button, a window opens up with some notebooks in it.
	You want to be in the "Function line plot" notebook tab, and inside you want to
	be on the "Functions / Expressions" notebook tab.
      </para>

      <figure id="lineplot-fig"> 
        <title>Create Plot Window</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/line_plot.png" format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <textobject> 
              <phrase>Shows the line plotting window.</phrase> 
            </textobject> 
          </mediaobject> 
        </screenshot> 
      </figure>

      <para>
	Into the text boxes just type in expressions where <userinput>x</userinput> is
	the independent variable.  You can also just give names of functions such as
	<userinput>cos</userinput> rather then having to type <userinput>cos(x)</userinput>.
	You can graph up to ten functions.  If you make a mistake and &appname; cannot
	parse the input it will signify this with a warning icon on the right of the text
	input box where the error occured, as well as giving you an error dialog.
	You can change the ranges of the dependent and independent variables in the bottom
	part of the dialog.
      </para>

      <para>
	Pressing the Plot button produces the following graph.
      </para>

      <figure id="lineplot2-fig"> 
        <title>Plot Window</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/line_plot_graph.png" format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <textobject> 
              <phrase>The graph produced.</phrase> 
            </textobject> 
          </mediaobject> 
        </screenshot> 
      </figure>

      <para>
	From here you can print out the plot, create encapsulated postscript
	or a PNG version of the plot or change the zoom.  If the dependent axis was
	not set correctly you can have &appname; fit it by finding out the extrema of
	the graphed functions.
      </para>

      <para>
	For plotting using the command line see the documentation of the
        <link linkend="gel-function-LinePlot">LinePlot</link> function.
      </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="genius-parametric-plots">
      <title>Parametric Plots</title>
      <para>
	In the create plot window, you can also choose the Parametric notebook
        tab to create two dimensional parametric plots.  This way you can
	plot a single parametric function.  You can either specify the
	points as x and y, or giving a single complex number.
      </para>

      <figure id="paramplot-fig"> 
        <title>Parametric Plots</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/parametric.png" format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <textobject> 
              <phrase>Parametric plotting tab in the Create Plot window.</phrase> 
            </textobject> 
          </mediaobject> 
        </screenshot> 
      </figure>

      <para>
	Here is an example of a parametric plot.  Similar operations can be
	done on such graphs as can be done on the other line plots.
      </para>

      <figure id="paramplot2-fig"> 
        <title></title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/parametric_graph.png" format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <textobject> 
              <phrase>Parametric plot produced</phrase> 
            </textobject> 
          </mediaobject> 
        </screenshot> 
      </figure>

      <para>
	For plotting using the command line see the documentation of the
        <link linkend="gel-function-LinePlotParametric">LinePlotParametric</link> or
        <link linkend="gel-function-LinePlotCParametric">LinePlotCParametric</link> function.
      </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="genius-surface-plots">
      <title>Surface Plots</title>
      <para>
	&appname; can also plot surfaces.  Select the "Surface plot" tab in the
	main notebook of the Create Plot window.  Here you can specify a single
	expression which should use either x and y as real independent variables
	or z as a complex variable (where x is the real part of z and y is the
	imaginary part).  For example to plot the modulus of the cosine
	function for complex parameters,
	you could enter <userinput>|cos(z)|</userinput>.  This would be
	equivalent to <userinput>|cos(x+1i*y)|</userinput>.
      </para>

      <figure id="surfaceplot-fig"> 
        <title>Surface plot</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/surface_graph.png" format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <textobject> 
              <phrase>Modulus of the complex cosine function.</phrase> 
            </textobject> 
          </mediaobject> 
        </screenshot> 
      </figure>

      <para>
	For plotting using the command line see the documentation of the
        <link linkend="gel-function-SurfacePlot">SurfacePlot</link> function.
      </para>
    </sect1>
